ANS Record Group 2: Curatorial, 1858-ongoing
American Numismatic Society
- Series 18: William E. Metcalf curator correspondence, 1954-2000, bulk 1982-2000; 10 cubic feet (10 boxes)
  Contains official correspondence relating to Metcalf’s role as ANS curator and chief curator, including letters filed by year (1982-1999) on topics such as inquiries from the general public about coins and numismatics; the fulfilling of orders for casts and photographs of ANS collections; the arranging of lecturers and students for the Summer Seminar; letters of support from Metcalf for individuals or projects; the arranging of his own lectures; and gifts of coins, books, and money. Also present are staff memorandums on various ANS policies and procedures sent by Metcalf as chief curator, some of which were circulated and initialed by staff (1982-1999); materials relating to the activities of a five-year plan and long-range planning committee, which includes a detailed memorandum from Metcalf addressing problems relating to the Society’s Audubon Terrace location and raising the possibility of the Society’s relocation (1991-1993); correspondence between Phil Mossman and Leslie Elam about James C. Spilman’s desire to divest himself of responsibility for the CNL (Colonial Newsletter) Foundation (1995-1996); general information for seminar students, including assessments of the restaurants in Washington Heights (William E. Metcalf, 1988, Box 7); a letter to John J. Pittman concerning the Bechtler press (P, 1986-1989, Box 7); correspondence pertaining to the sale by Johns Hopkins University of the John Work Garrett coin collection (Evergreen House, 1978-1979, Box 2); materials relating to the Juan Suros and William Sheldon ANS coin thefts (Box 2); and items relating to an insurance claim for coins said to be stolen but that may have in fact been in the possession of the ANS (Travelers Company, 1988). Also includes some files that Metcalf may have been using for research, such as the earliest materials found in these records: correspondence, notes, and photographs relating to several hoards (1954-, Box 3), and letters and notes from Alexander Veglery to George Miles on Byzantine seals (1963).
- Series 19: Miscellaneous curatorial records, 1900-1940; 1 box
  Inventories; Correspondence; Photographs; Gorman, Michael
  Various materials relating to ANS coin and other collections. Contains two handwritten inventories, one entitled “List of Pamphlets Etc. on Bottom of Case” (2 pages) and the other a listing by section coins contained in a cabinet (27 pages) (circa 1900); an inventory of ANS token and store card holdings (circa 1903); a list of duplicate coins from the numismatic section of the Public Library, Museum, and Art Gallery of South Australia; photographs, a clipping, and descriptions relating to a theft of medals, including life-saving medals, from the ANS (1939) (includes a receipt and letters relating to a gift from Captain Michael Gorman, 1911-1912); and correspondence resulting from an attempt to contact people who had mailed in coins unsolicited nearly thirty years earlier (1940).
    nnan0115/c_4b4109176e8b8f3dda899354005a85f6
  - Pamphlet and coin inventories, circa 1900
  - ANS token and store card holdings and accessions, ca. 1903
  - Public Library, Museum, and Art Gallery of South Australia--Offer and list of duplicate coins
  - Coin theft, 1939
  - Correspondence regarding unclaimed coins and other items, 1940